Guide to the Hiram Barker Papers, 1857-1895
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Hiram Barker papers 1857-1895
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Barker, Hiram.
3.0 linear feet Extent: 1880 Items
Prominent businessman and banker from Farmington, New Hampshire; established and managed multiple business investments in New Hampshire, the Dakota Territory, Florida, Iowa, Illinois, Kansas, Missouri, Nebraska, and Minnesota in the late 19th century. Collection consists chiefly of business correspondence dating from circa 1871-1886, almost all directed to Hiram Barker in New Hampshire, although in some cases Barker was the author. Correspondents include managers of Barker's businesses and investments in the Western territories and states of Dakota, Florida, Illinois, Iowa, Kansas, Missouri, Nebraska, and Minnesota, and other firms with whom Barker did business. Topics revolve around business matters and trends in New Hampshire, the Western states and territories, including but not limited to real estate loans and investments, land investments, banking and loans, financial difficulties such as loan defaults, and ranching or farming in the Western states listed above. A smaller group of letters concern personal and family matters of both the Barker and Hayes family, into which Barker had married. Arranged by state in alphabetical order.
RL.00080
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Provenance
The Hiram Barker Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 1983.
Biographical Note
Hiram Barker was a prominent businessman and banker from Farmington, New Hampshire. He established and managed multiple business investments in New Hampshire, the Dakota Territory, Florida, Iowa, Illinois, Kansas, Missouri, Nebraska, and Minnesota in the late 19th century.
Collection Overview
Collection consists chiefly of business correspondence dating from circa 1871-1886, almost all directed to Hiram Barker in New Hampshire, although in some cases Barker was the author. Correspondents include managers of Barker's businesses and investments in the Western territories and states of Dakota, Illinois, Iowa, Kansas, Missouri, Nebraska, and Minnesota, and other firms with whom Barker did business. Topics revolve around business matters and trends in New Hampshire, the Western states and territories, including but not limited to real estate loans and investments, land investments, banking and loans, financial difficulties such as loan defaults, and ranching or farming in the Western states listed above. Businesses mentioned include the Central Bank of Kansas, the Citizens Bank in Iowa, Topeka Loan and Investment Company in Kansas, and the Eclipse Milling Company in Minnesota. There are also business papers relating to Florida, including land investments in 1885, some of which involve the governor of Florida and New Hampshire native George Franklin Drew, who may have also witnessed the will of Reuben Hayes for which Barker was an executor. A small group of letters concern personal and family matters of both the Barker and Hayes family, into which Barker had married. A set of folders marked in the last box marked Miscellany contain chiefly business receipts and unidentified letters dating from 1857-1895. Arranged by state in alphabetical order.
Subject Headings
Barker, Hiram; Barker family (N.H.); Hayes family (N.H.); Businesspeople -- New Hampshire -- Correspondence; Agriculture -- Middle West -- Economic aspects -- 19th century; Banks and banking -- United States -- 19th century; Industrialization -- West (U.S.) -- History; Industries -- Middle West -- History -- 19th century; Florida -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; South Dakota -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Illinois -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Iowa -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Missouri -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Kansas -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; Middle West -- Economic development -- 19th century; Minnesota -- Economic conditions -- 19th century; New Hampshire -- Economic conditions -- 19th century
Contents of Collection
- Hiram Barker Papers, 1857-1895, (6 boxes)
  Arranged in alphabetical order by state name. The last set of folders contains miscellaneous business receipts and unidentified or illegible correspondence from various locations.
  - Collection Information Folder (Box 1)
    Detailed descriptions related to largest groups of correspondence, including extracts transcribed from letters, details on family history, and comments on highlights and on the correspondents.
  - Dakota Territory (South Dakota), 1880s, (2 boxes)
    - Brule County Bank correspondence and legal/financial papers, 1882-1886 (Box 1)
    - Brule County miscellaneous business papers (Box 2)
    - Madison Bank & American Mortgage and Investment Company correspondence, 1885-1886 (Box 2)
    - Other Dakota business records (Box 2)
  - Florida business papers, 1880s
  - Illinois, 1871-1885 and undated
    - B. L. Pease correspondence, 1871-1885 and undated (Box 2)
    - B. L. Pease, legal and financial papers (Box 2)
  - Iowa, 1871-1886
    - Citizens Bank correspondence, 1871-1886 (Box 3)
    - Citizens Bank legal and financial papers (Box 3)
    - W. G. Tyrrell correspondence (Box 3)
    - Other Iowa business papers (Box 3)
  - Kansas, 1880s
    - Central Bank of Kansas correspondence, circa 1882-1886 (Box 3)
    - Central Bank of Kansas legal and financial papers (Box 3)
    - Topeka Loan and Investment correspondence, 1884-1886 (Box 3)
  - Kansas and Missouri, 1880s
    - A. H. Gossard correspondence, 1882-1887 and undated (Box 4)
    - A. H. Gossard legal and financial papers (Box 4)
    - Other business papers (Box 4)
  - Massachusetts, 1800s
    - Business papers, chiefly correspondence from other firms, 1800s (Box 4)
  - Minnesota, 1880s
    - Eclipse Milling Company correspondence, circa 1882-1886 (Box 4)
    - Eclipse Milling Company miscellaneous business papers (Box 4)
    - Other Minnesota business papers (Box 4)
  - Nebraska, 1880s
    - George Bickford (Loup City, S.D.) correspondence, circa 1882-1886 (Box 5)
    - Other Nebraska business papers (Box 5)
  - New Hampshire, 1880s
    - Hayes family, legal and financial papers (Box 5)
    - Hiram Barker, local business, legal and financial papers, (5 folders) (Box 6)
    - Hiram Barker, personal and family correspondence, circa 1882-1886 (Box 6)
  - Other Papers
    Chiefly business receipts, and several pieces of unidentified or illegible pieces of correspondence. Includes receipts and bills of sale from the late 1850s and 1860s, but the majority are in the latter part of the 19th century.
    - Other papers, 1857-1895 (Box 6)